<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<notes>
<p>
In <em>CScout</em> from version 2.2 and onward you can
you can also use the supplied tool <em>csmake</em> to
directly generate <em>CScout</em> processing scripts by monitoring a project's
make-based build process.
For this to work your project's build must (probably) be based
on a Unix or Unix-like system, and use <em>make</em> and <em>gcc</em>.
The make process can also invoke <em>ld</em>, <em>ar</em>, and <em>mv</em>.
Recursive <em>make</em> invocations among different directories are
also supported.
</p><p>
The way to use <em>csmake</em> is fairly simple.
You first arrange for performing a full build, for example by running
</p>
<fmtcode ext="sh">
make clean
</fmtcode>
<p>
Then, instead of running <code>make</code> on the project's top-level
directory you run <code>csmake</code>.
When the build process has finished, <em>csmake</em> will leave in
the directory where you started it a <em>CScout</em> processing script
named <code>make.cs</code>.
</p><p>
<em>csmake</em> has been used out-of-the-box to run <em>CScout</em> on
the Linux kernel version 2.6.11.4 and the Apache httpd version 2.2.3.
It has also been used to process the FreeBSD 7-CURRENT kernel under
its three Tier-1 architecture configurations by cross-compiling each
configuration separately and merging the resulting <em>CScout</em>
processing scripts.
This is the shell script that did the job.
</p>
<fmtcode ext="sh">
for a in amd64 i386 sparc64
do
        (
                cd sys/$a/conf/
                make LINT
                config LINT
        )
        export MAKEOBJDIRPREFIX=/home/dds/src/fbsd-head/obj/$a
        csmake buildkernel TARGET_ARCH=$a  KERNCONF=LINT
        mv make.cs make.$a.cs
done
cat make.*.cs >all.cs
sed -n 's/#pragma process "\(.*hack.c\)"/\1/p' all.cs | xargs touch
cscout all.cs
</fmtcode>

<p>
	Finally, for processing a couple of C files, you can create a
	project file by invoking the <em>cscc</em> tool with the
	arguments you would pass to the C compiler.
</p>
</notes>
