<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<notes>
<em>CScout</em>  implements the
C language as defined in ANSI X3.159-1989.
In addition, it supports the following extensions.
Many GCC extensions also apply to LLVM.
<ol>
<li> Preprocessor directives can appear within a call to a function-like macro (GCC)</li>
<li> Initializers and compound literals can be empty (GCC)</li>
<li> The <code>alignof</code> operator can be used on types (GCC) </li>
<li> A declaration expression as the first element of a <code>for</code> statement (C99)
<li> The <code>restrict</code> qualifier and the <code>inline</code> specifier (C99)
<li> The <code>_Bool</code> type (C99)
<li> The <code>_Thread_local</code> storage class specifier (C11)
<li> The <code>_Generic</code> generic selection expression (C11)
<li> Support <code>static</code> and other qualifiers in array type declarations (C99)
<li> Initialization designators (C99)
<li> Array initialization designators can include ranges (GCC) </li>
<li> ANSI-style function definitions can be nested (GCC) (GCC also allows
nested K&R-style function definitions)</li>
<li> The equals sign following an initializer designator is optional (GCC) </li>
<li> Array and structure initialization (GCC)
<li> Compound literals (C99)
<li> Declarations can be intermixed with statements (C99).
<li> Recognise <code>__atribute__(__unused__)</code> for determining which
identifiers should not be reported as unused (GCC).
<li> <code>//</code> line comments (common extension)
<li> <code>__asm__</code> blocks (GCC)
<li> <code>enum</code> lists ending with a comma (common extension)
<li> Anonymous <code>struct/union</code> members (GCC, Microsoft C)
<li> Allow <code>case</code> expression ranges (GCC).
<li> An enumeration list can be empty (Microsoft C)
<li>Allow braces around scalar initializers (common extension).</li>
<li> Indirect <code>goto</code> targets and the label address-of operator (GCC).
<li> <code>__typeof</code> keyword (GCC)
<li> <code>__typeof__unqual__</code> keyword (GCC)
<li> The ‘##’ token paste operator deletes the comma when placed between a comma and an empty variable argument (GCC)
<li> <code>__VA_OPT__ </code> function macro (C23)
<li> A compound statement in brackets can be an expression (GCC)
<li> Macros expanding from <code>/##/</code> into
<code>//</code> are then treated as a line comment (Microsoft C)
<li> Exception handling using the <code>__try __except __finally __leave</code> keywords (Microsoft C) </li>
<li> <code>#include_next</code> preprocessor directive (GCC)
<li> <code>#warning</code> preprocessor directive (GCC)
<li> Variable number of arguments preprocessor macros
(support for both the GCC and the C99 syntax)
<li> Allow empty member declarations in aggregates (GCC)
<li> <code>long long</code> type (common extension)
<li> A semicolon can appear as a declatation (common extension)
<li> An aggregate declaration body can be empty (GCC)
<li> Aggregate member initialization using the member: value syntax (GCC)
<li> Statement labels do not require a statement following them (GCC)
<li> #ident preprocessor directive (GCC)
<li> Allow assignment to case expressions (common extension)
<li> Accept an empty translation unit (common extension).
<li> Support locally declared labels (<code>__label__</code>) (GCC).
<li> The second argument of a conditional expression can be omitted (GCC).
<li> Dereferencing a function yields a function (common extension).
<li> The <code>__simd</code> type qualifier can be used to define
     basic types that are also indexable, similarly to the GCC
     extension <code>__attribute__((__vector_size__(…)))</code>.
</ol>
Many other compiler-specific extensions are handled by suitable
macro definitions in the <em>CScout</em> initialization file.
</notes>
