<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<notes>
<em>CScout</em> can create include graphs that list how files include each
other.

<p>
Two global options
specify the format of the include graph and the content
on each graph's node.
Through these options you can obtain graphs in
<ul>
<li>plain text form: suitable for processing with other tools,</li>
<li> HTML: suitable for browsing via <em>CScout</em>,</li>
<li> dot: suitable for generating high-quality graphics files,</li>
<li> SVG: suitable for graphical browsing, if your browser supports this format, and</li>
<li> GIF: suitable for viewing on SVG-challenged browsers.</li>
</ul>
All diagrams follow the notation
<pre>
including file -> included file
</pre>

<p>
Two links on the main page
(file include graph - writable files and
file include graph - all files)
can give you the include graphs of the complete program.
For programs larger than a hundred thousand lines,
these graphs are only useful in their textual form.
In their graphical form, even with node information disabled,
they can only serve to give you a rough idea of how the program is
structured.
The following image depicts how writable (non-system) files are
included in the <em>awk</em> source code.
<br> <img src="awkinc.gif"><br>
and the following is a part of the include file structure of the
Windows Research Kernel
<br> <img src="wrk-inc.gif"><p>

More useful are typically the include graphs that can be generated for
individual files.
These can allow you to see what paths can possibly lead to the inclusion
of a given file (include graph of all including files) or what files
a given file includes (include graph of all included files).

(call graph of all callers),
which functions can be reached starting from a given function,
and how functions in a given file relate to each other.
<p>
As an example, the following diagram depicts all files that
<code>main.c</code> includes
<br> <img src="main-inc.gif">
<br>
while the following diagrams shows all the files including
(directly or indirectly)
<code>proto.h</code>.
<br> <img src="proto-inc.gif"><p>
</notes>
